[SPEAKER_00]: So, this is a sutta maybe for monks, really, a discussion for monks.
[SPEAKER_00]: Maybe they would understand it a bit more.
[SPEAKER_00]: But in any case, it's called One in Training.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the Buddha says,
[SPEAKER_00]: Amongst this recitation of more than 150 training rules, he means the Patimokkha, comes up every fortnight in reference to which sons of good families desiring the goal train themselves.
[SPEAKER_00]: There are these three trainings under which all that is gathered.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which three?
[SPEAKER_00]: The training in heightened virtue, the training in heightened mind, and the training in heightened discernment.
[SPEAKER_00]: These are the three trainings under which all that is gathered.
[SPEAKER_00]: So there is a case where a monk is wholly accomplished, fully accomplished in virtue,
[SPEAKER_00]: He's not ignoring.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why is that?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because I...
[SPEAKER_00]: So,
[SPEAKER_00]: Why is that?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because I have not declared that to be a disqualification in these circumstances.
[SPEAKER_00]: Meaning, being wholly accomplished in virtue doesn't disqualify.
[SPEAKER_00]: But as for the training rules that are basic to the holy life and proper to the holy life, he's one of permanent virtue, one of steadfast virtue.
[SPEAKER_00]: Having undertaken them, he trains in reference to the training rules.
[SPEAKER_00]: And with the ending of the first three fetters, he's a stream-winner, a sotāpanna, never again destined for the states of woe, certain, headed for self-awakening.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it goes on through that, through the different levels of attainment, all the way up to Arahant Shastri.
[SPEAKER_00]: On the basis of that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Accomplished in... fully accomplished in virtue, fully accomplished in...
[SPEAKER_00]: Mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: What is it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Heightened mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: Heightened discernment.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, that would follow.
[SPEAKER_01]: In the same sense that the, you know, the...
[SPEAKER_01]: And at the end of that sutta, he says, those who are partially accomplished attain a path.
[SPEAKER_01]: Those who are whole, fully accomplished,
[SPEAKER_00]: The training rules, I tell you, are not in vain.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's the important part.
[SPEAKER_01]: The rules that are essence of the training are basically the eight precepts.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whenever the Guru would talk about, you know, the wise men of the past, the virtuous people of the past, it's it's the eight precepts are these principles, but then you can have many other rules in in in in the in the monastic vinaya, you have many other rules, but they're all kind of within that.
[SPEAKER_00]: The one, the rules that matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then you have the circumstantial, social rules and so on, minor rules.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the ones that matter for the training are basically the ones that are around lust, aversion, distraction and delusion.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, yes, that's meant for the monks, but actually even a lay person, if they become accomplished in eight precepts, can expect the same.
[SPEAKER_01]: Heightened mind and heightened discernment.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, many lay people in the suttas were anāgāmīs, they were teaching monks, the new monks, because they were so developed.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, so what is that development?
[SPEAKER_01]: Is it the technical letter of the rule, you know, prescribed by the contemporary tradition?
[SPEAKER_01]: What is it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Where is it?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what is that accomplishment?
[SPEAKER_01]: What does it make you accomplished?
[SPEAKER_01]: Is it knowing the letter of every rule and looking for every technicality?
[SPEAKER_01]: Or knowing the state of mind and intention behind your actions, which is closer?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, whenever people are latching onto technicalities, and the latter of the rules, it's when the intention for the state of mind is either obscured, not taking responsibility for, or blatantly just to be avoided.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you don't feel responsible, because this is the tradition that I follow, this is the rules that I follow, this is the letter that I follow, and I don't think...
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't need to think for myself.
[SPEAKER_01]: And because of that, you can follow such rules in such manner for a hundred years, have, like, the full ordination, the highest approval, and still not be accomplished in virtue.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's exactly what Śrīla Prabhupāda says.
[SPEAKER_01]: Taking on virtue,
[SPEAKER_01]: As a sense of external duty, for which you're not allowing yourself to feel responsible for, internally.
[SPEAKER_01]: And why would a person not allow themselves to feel responsible for that?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because the moment you become responsible, you become liable to doubt.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's exactly why Sīla Bhāgavata Paramāsa is bundled with the factor of doubt.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you actually manage
[SPEAKER_01]: To break yourself away from the dependence on the external letter and take responsibility for the virtue, you will creating a basis for overcoming the factor of doubt.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you don't allow yourself to step away from it in that correct sense, in that correct direction, you will never overcome doubt.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because the reason why the duty is imposed by yourself to yourself is so the doubt cannot arise.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you often see that.
[SPEAKER_01]: When a mind that's dependent on the letter, somebody points out that that letter might be wrong, they're overwhelmed.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, we witness it many times.
[SPEAKER_01]: Overwhelmed with the existential doubt.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because they realize everything leading up to that was based on that letter saying what it says, so I didn't feel responsible for.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yet now, somebody just questions that.
[SPEAKER_01]: They don't even prove that the letter of your rule is wrong.
[SPEAKER_01]: They just start questioning it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you are shaking.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if that doesn't concern you, means you lack even basic authenticity, basic self-awareness.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why there is no right view for you.
[SPEAKER_01]: So you need to understand that, that yes, you learned the letter of the rules,
[SPEAKER_01]: But, depending how, like, how far you're gonna go into the letter of the rules, and why?
[SPEAKER_01]: Is it because I'm not really still understanding the rule?
[SPEAKER_01]: Sure, go further.
[SPEAKER_01]: Is it, no, I understand the rule, but I want more technicalities to prevent me from myself and from my own mind?
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, you want to avoid the practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that's where samādhi is, as we said before.
[SPEAKER_01]: Things that want to overwhelm the mind, the monk doesn't let the mind being overwhelmed.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's his practice of samādhi.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you understood the rule, you understand the 8 precepts, you understand the 10 precepts, you understand 150 training rules.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you're not clear about some rule, you clarify it, that's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, you practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: You practice in a way by keep making sure when you're about to act, you act according with those rules, or you act according with non-greed, non-aversion, non-delusion.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you break it, you see where you broke it, you see why you broke it, and you don't need to depend on technicality, because you're always aware of your intention behind the actions.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, if somebody points out technicality allows you this, but it's like, it doesn't.
[SPEAKER_01]: The state of mind doesn't allow you to do that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you actually stop looking, if you start looking at the context of the rules, eight precepts or 150 precepts,
[SPEAKER_01]: And maintain the context of the rules in your mind, there will be no loopholes for you, and there will be no need for the loopholes.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you start looking at the letter that gets proliferated more and more and more into this definition of a sub-definition of a sub-definition, then, all of it, it will be about loopholes.
[SPEAKER_01]: It will be about things that are left not addressed, and you know they come under the same context, but you have drifted away from that context so much now,
[SPEAKER_01]: Into these particulars, that you lost the sight of the forest, pretty much.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's exactly when people and monks become technical.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, technically, I'm not breaking the rule and stuff.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like, what is the state of mind behind that action?
[SPEAKER_01]: You are breaking the virtue.
[SPEAKER_01]: End of story.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is no accomplishment in virtue, unless you take the virtue on that level of the mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: But people confuse learning about the rules, learning about technicalities, for keeping the rules and keeping the technicalities.
[SPEAKER_01]: In other words, they feel justified in not taking it personally, in not taking responsibility for it, but projecting and keeping responsibility on the level of, well, that's the tradition, that's the authority, that's how it's been for hundreds of years.
[SPEAKER_01]: Doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can choose to accept the tradition, the traditional rules, the traditional standards.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's all fine.
[SPEAKER_01]: But even if you do so, you still have to recognize that you're responsible for that.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're responsible for either choosing to interpret things for yourself, for either choosing to follow this commentary, for either choosing to follow someone else's interpretation or someone else's tradition.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's on you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Nothing justifies you in choosing that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in other words, you need to recognize that, eh...
[SPEAKER_01]: Whether you you understand it for yourself directly, or whether you follow someone else's interpretation, you need to know why you are doing it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That needs to be clear to you.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if I ask you, oh, do you keep the eight precepts?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: What about the fifth precept?
[SPEAKER_01]: What's your standard on it?
[SPEAKER_01]: How do you understand such and such circumstance?
[SPEAKER_01]: And you tell me, well, I follow the tradition of such and such teacher.
[SPEAKER_01]: I, as a dog, that's fine.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why?
[SPEAKER_01]: You should be able to tell me why do you follow that.
[SPEAKER_01]: In other words, how is that way of like following that particular interpretation or the rule or take on the rule, how is that feeding your accomplishment in virtue directly?
[SPEAKER_01]: How is that connected to it?
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't just say I follow because he's a great teacher.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, yeah, but what is the benefit of following that?
[SPEAKER_01]: Do you see that for yourself?
[SPEAKER_01]: Or you're just going by mere reputation and mere tradition and hearsay?
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is, you know, the Buddha said many times, something you shouldn't really do, unless you're very unwise.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, yeah, follow, like, you know, clarify whatever else, but never feel justified on just, oh, well, I belong to this great tradition now, and these are our standards, and that's the end of the game there.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why?
[SPEAKER_01]: Why do I keep these standards?
[SPEAKER_01]: Do I keep them authentically, individually, personally, internally?
[SPEAKER_01]: In which case, I don't need the tradition and the standards, because it's kept on this level, not on the level of traditional behavior.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's how exactly what was said.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you actually accomplish yourself on that level, in that virtue, where you're not shying away from doubt, but willing to endure it, clarifying the context, maintaining the context, not proliferating the rule to prevent you from having doubt arise in your mind again, or I will never do that again.
[SPEAKER_01]: Wait, but it wasn't an offense.
[SPEAKER_01]: It was not an issue.
[SPEAKER_01]: It wasn't even rooted in greed, aversion, delusion.
[SPEAKER_01]: But why am I doubting it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that's what doubt is.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's an irrational mind, a hindrance, that tries to throw you away, tries to make you act out of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And here you are, acting out of it, because now you're redefining and making new rules, so you will never do stuff that you know was nothing wrong with.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just because you doubted on account of it, and you never... you don't know how to deal with the doubt.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, by taking the virtue wrongly, you will not be able to deal with the doubt, because of which you keep taking the virtue wrongly, because of which you can't deal with the doubt.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's no samādhi.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's no... No samādhi, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Absolutely no samādhi, because there is no accomplishment.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you take the virtue rightly, endure the doubt, don't act out of the doubt, sustain the context of the virtue... No.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you know.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know what it is, but the mind pressures you to find out more, look into technique, create this, create that, act left, act right, avoid, prevent.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you sustain that and not act out of it, you will become accomplished in the virtue.
[SPEAKER_01]: And basically, how did you do that?
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, that's already the practice of samādhi.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not moving in regard to the mind that wants to move you.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's what the Buddha said.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just, if somebody is accomplished, at least in that basis, three factors will have to be destroyed.
[SPEAKER_01]: You cannot not be a sotāpanna if you have taken virtue on that level and endured it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you will certainly not be a sotāpanna if you've taken virtue on the level of the external letter of the law, the rule, the tradition, the authority, the ājā, the senior monk, whatever else.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if they were right, by the way, in the standards that they laid upon you, if you took it externally, there is no basis for your virtue to actually take place.
[SPEAKER_00]: So it's like, if you... the first precept of not harming, not killing a living being, why do you keep that?
[SPEAKER_00]: Why is that wrong?
[SPEAKER_00]: And if you don't know why,
[SPEAKER_00]: You cannot be accomplished in it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just kind of circumstantially taken that external rule.
[SPEAKER_01]: You learn them circumstantially.
[SPEAKER_01]: You investigate them circumstantially, but once you start keeping them, no, you need to know for yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, this needs to be seen personally.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, why this is not done?
[SPEAKER_01]: Why it's not good to do this?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's the thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you see what is unwholesome, what is wholesome.
[SPEAKER_00]: That is your discernment thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well... And the clearer that is... That's what you're going to start seeing.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're going to start seeing wholesome is wholesome, unwholesome is unwholesome, because you're seeing the root of that which makes it unwholesome, what makes it wholesome.
[SPEAKER_00]: Right, right.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you will not see that if you just block it and say, well, this is our tradition, this is my culture, this is what a Buddhist person does.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like, well, okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's, that's
[SPEAKER_01]: That level of, oh, I am such and such.
[SPEAKER_01]: I identify with that religion, with that observance, with that rule.
[SPEAKER_01]: I keep it.
[SPEAKER_01]: No questions asked.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it makes you feel safe.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, exactly, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, oh, questioning means you don't want to keep it.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: Questioning means I want to know what I keep.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, there's no, there's no justification for you assuming cynical reasons for my questioning.
[SPEAKER_01]: Unless it's your own cynical mind putting that over there.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: I want to understand what I keep.
[SPEAKER_01]: But for many people, even questioning to understand what will make you... like, do I need to keep this?
[SPEAKER_01]: Do I want to keep this?
[SPEAKER_01]: Do I want to be a monk?
[SPEAKER_01]: Do I want to practice?
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's something also they... it makes you unpleasant, makes you doubtful.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you refuse to think about it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You refuse to question.
[SPEAKER_01]: You just double down.
[SPEAKER_01]: This is my duty.
[SPEAKER_01]: This is the tradition.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you double down on your own sīlavāta paramāsa.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you look at the beginning of the monastic order, there were no rules.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, of course.
[SPEAKER_01]: Dhamma was clear.
[SPEAKER_01]: It was not obscured.
[SPEAKER_01]: People knew exactly what behaviors were in line with it and what behaviors weren't.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, so... and that... that... that basic... you can boil it down to... don't do anything unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_00]: Know what unwholesome is and don't do it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why also, as the thing sort of progressed, back in the Buddhist time, that whole need for, like, you know, a new monk would have to spend, like, five years training with senior monk.
[SPEAKER_01]: Somebody that accepted Him.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, yes, an untrained mind will start, like, you know, will not be able to necessarily even sustain the right context.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you want to spend the first few years learning that context, but you don't want to spend the first few years just learning the letter of some tradition that you got into, without actually understanding why you're doing it, or developing that authentic recognition that it's still up to you whether you keep it or not, and to what extent, and you want to see the intentions behind your actions there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that's often like, okay, so, basically, even that process of learning for five years from a senior monk has become like a mechanical letter of stuff you go through, without actually learning, and without monk teaching you either.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, just for five years, you're under someone's, like, tutorship, but in reality, it's just basically learning of that external form, external letter,
[SPEAKER_01]: Not being taught responsibility behind, not being taught how to see the responsibility behind, and how to take it on, in which case you would... you wouldn't even need, then, the further definitions of these rules, because you would be unable to ignore the unwholesome intentions before you act, so you wouldn't act.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the training.
[SPEAKER_01]: But even training has become like a... like a traditional form.
[SPEAKER_01]: In the same sense, external, on a level of sīlabhāta paramāsa, on the level of virtue.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's it's it's just it's like a dead matter in that sense, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, individually, everybody can rekindle it for themselves, if they actually exactly studied in the suttas.
[SPEAKER_01]: Reading the origin stories and so on, and you start seeing... you get... you get in that livable context, and you know, it's about the state of mind, it's about the perception, how I perceive it, what I choose to do.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not about, you know, commentary of a sub-commentary of a sub-commentary defining this is allowable, and then another commentary defining that is not allowable, and me now spending nights and figuring out who might be more right than these two.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: Where is my intention rooted?
[SPEAKER_01]: You got your answer.
[SPEAKER_01]: And on top of that, not just that you got the answer as to what is the right thing to do, you also started accomplishing yourself in virtue, which is a basis for satipaṭṭhāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you don't have the right view, if you have not reached the fruits of stream-entry, it's because you haven't been accomplished in virtue.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's a good news, because now you know what to do.
[SPEAKER_01]: Accomplish yourself in virtue.
[SPEAKER_01]: How do you do that?
[SPEAKER_01]: By taking it personally.
[SPEAKER_01]: Learning the rules, sure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Learning the interpretation, sure.
[SPEAKER_01]: But not relying on the word of the rule, the authority of interpretation or tradition, as this is why it's kept.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's kept because I choose to keep it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I choose to keep it because I see direct relationship between that and wholesome mind, or not that and unwholesome mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that will inevitably, initially, certainly, bring the doubt, bring that sense of, oh, so I could just decide to not keep...
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you're gonna feel the weight of keeping that.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's how you become accomplished.
[SPEAKER_00]: But in also doing that, you will eventually begin to see which rules are actually obsolete.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, but you wouldn't really worry about that.
[SPEAKER_00]: You wouldn't, but you would, as the Buddha said...
[SPEAKER_00]: It would become self-evident, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: The minor rules...
[SPEAKER_01]: The minor rules will not affect him, and he will know that.
[SPEAKER_01]: He'd still confess, he wouldn't have an issue.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sometimes the problem is, if a person is not accomplished in the virtue, and then get a sense of righteousness, of discovering of this, what we are saying, and then they just try to form a new tradition of dismissing all the traditions and interpreting things for yourself, in a same external manner of sīlabāta paramāsa.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't need to change anything.
[SPEAKER_01]: You need to take things personally, and then what needs to be changed will happen by itself.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you have the authentic mind, you have the accomplishment in virtue, samādhi is there, what change occurs will be the right change.
[SPEAKER_01]: You wouldn't have to do it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You wouldn't have to act out of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: In other words, you would naturally drift away from things that are unsuitable, traditions that are unsuitable, practices that are unsuitable, into the directions that are suitable for the right view, for this passion and for everything else.
[SPEAKER_01]: Without needing to make a big deal out of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you wouldn't become this self-righteous.
[SPEAKER_01]: Impossible, impossible, impossible.
[SPEAKER_01]: You would not either become scared.
[SPEAKER_01]: You wouldn't be self-righteous trying to change everybody, but if everybody comes after you in account of it, you wouldn't shy away, because you know what's right.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you wouldn't need to change the established external norms, but you wouldn't be afraid to challenge them either, because it's not rooted in your conceit.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's rooted in recognition of what the accomplishment of virtue is and the right view.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you were to question those things, you wouldn't just, you know, be on a crusade to change the... as I said, but if it comes up to it, you wouldn't be afraid of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: If circumstances bring it up, you will have no issues dealing with it and addressing it.
[SPEAKER_00]: In... there's another sutta, Samana Pāla Sutta.
[SPEAKER_00]: The Buddha says, a mendicant, a monk, thus accomplished in virtue, sees no danger in any quarter in regards to their virtuous restraint.
[SPEAKER_00]: It is like a king who has defeated his enemies.
[SPEAKER_00]: He sees no danger from his enemies in any direction.
[SPEAKER_00]: In that same way, a monk thus accomplished in virtue sees no danger in any direction in regards to their virtuous restraint.
[SPEAKER_00]: When they have this aggregate, this domain of noble virtue,
[SPEAKER_00]: The monk who has ceased to depend on the external circumstances, external authority, external definitions, external rules, external requirements,
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: Knowing right is right, wrong is wrong.
[SPEAKER_01]: Wholesome is wholesome, unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: Means knowing, lust, aversion, delusion sufficiently enough.
[SPEAKER_01]: To always see it and not act out of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You practice that, you will become accomplished in that.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, doesn't matter the circumstance, doesn't matter what quarter the circumstances arrive at you, from what direction, there is no danger, because you're not depending on that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if somebody comes and starts questioning the certain interpretation of a letter, of a rule, it doesn't matter, because that's not what your virtue was based on.
[SPEAKER_01]: It was based on you not doing anything out of intention or greed, aversion, delusion.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, even if somebody says, look, all these rules were actually wrong, they were written by somebody later, inserted there, they're not right, makes no difference.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you would actually know that they were right, even if somebody did edit them rightly, because they're according to the standard of dhamma.
[SPEAKER_01]: Standard of dispassion, disenchantment, non-greed, non-aversion, non-delusion.
[SPEAKER_01]: But for as long as you put the letter first, the external authority of Sīla Bhārata Paramāsa first, you will not see this.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you're refusing to take responsibility for it, and allow it to become internal, because it's unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_01]: The weight of it is unpleasant, the weight of responsibility is unpleasant, the pressure is unpleasant, the liability to doubt is unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you have to endure it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Developing of samādhi is unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_01]: And same.
[SPEAKER_01]: Eight precepts for a layperson, same.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why often the Buddha would not even overly define things, because if the mind isn't... hasn't strayed from the right context of non-greed, non-aversion, non-delusion, recognizes that state of mind, doesn't act out of it regardless of what the action might be, you don't need extra and extra layers of definitions and words and interpretations and meanings, because the meaning is there, the context is there, it's clear.
[SPEAKER_01]: So that's why practically eight precepts are modern enough, certainly for anāgāmī.
[SPEAKER_01]: In a lay setting, for a monk, yeah, you'll be an arahant, accomplished to the same virtue, the same thread.
[SPEAKER_00]: I like the way it's said, like, that he is...
[SPEAKER_00]: He who is accomplished or attained in possesses the aggregate of virtue, the aggregate of virtue.
[SPEAKER_00]: He has created this aggregate.
[SPEAKER_01]: He created an aggregate, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: That now he can recognize.
[SPEAKER_01]: He can recognize and he's encouraged to recollect and dwell because it will re-inspire confidence and sense of safety and gladness that will then bring samādhi and so on to fulfillment.
[SPEAKER_01]: And clear understanding of what's... what's what.
[SPEAKER_01]: But not without it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that is, again, that is the entire practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: Your samādhi comes out of it, your pañña comes out of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: The more you do it, the more you perfect it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like greed, aversion, delusion, removed from physical, verbal and mental.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what dhamma is.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, start on the physical level.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that is your samādhi, that is your pañña, that is your practice towards sotāpatti and higher.
[SPEAKER_00]: You never give...
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not found elsewhere.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not found after.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's right there and then.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not done for just a short period of time and then... No.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what I'm saying.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's better to even, like, if you, if you, oh, hate priesthood too much, as a layperson, take the five priesthoods for the rest of your life.
[SPEAKER_01]: But not for the weekend.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because means you never really allow... you never really consider changing the order of what's important to you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sensuality is important to you.
[SPEAKER_01]: So now you realize that, yeah, precepts are good and maybe I should do something about it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then you only do it like for two or three days or five days.
[SPEAKER_01]: Means, oh, you're just sort of... toying with it, while at the same time, refusing to allow the actual... no, sensuality to be put second.
[SPEAKER_00]: And my precepts will now be first for the rest of my life.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's important.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what it is.
[SPEAKER_01]: He undertakes the training of virtue.
[SPEAKER_01]: You need to take it in that ultimate sense.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not this conditional, I'll do it a bit until I get meditation experience or something.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, no.
[SPEAKER_01]: In that sense, it's better to have five precepts, but for the rest of your life.
[SPEAKER_01]: Than to, like, no precepts and then super austere level of celibacy for ten days and then, boom, no precepts at all.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not accomplishing anything, really.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, I mean, you're obviously trying, so that's a good thing, I suppose.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you want to recognize the gradual training starts gradually and starts in that responsible sense, but absolutely non-negotiable sense.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's like, okay, so what can I sustain and what am I able to... can I make this determination for the rest of my life?
[SPEAKER_01]: To not kill, cheat, lie, steal, misconduct, take intoxicants.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if just that thought scares you, oh, I can't do this...
[SPEAKER_01]: You need to do that first, before you can even consider direction of any practice whatsoever.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that is the practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: You considering that, is the practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: You making yourself being able to determine to keep the five precepts for the rest of your life, or eight precepts for the rest of your life, is the beginning of your accomplishment in virtue.
[SPEAKER_01]: It won't come up, come, come, like, it won't result on its own, somehow.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you got a, you know, a very, very, very potent meditation method, that will now, if you adhere to it, just create this virtue for you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Another sutta called the restraint of the patimokkha.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then a certain bhikkhu approached the blessed one and asked him,
[SPEAKER_00]: Venerable Sir, it would be good if the Blessed One would teach me the dhamma in brief, so that, having heard the dhamma from the Blessed One, I might dwell alone, withdrawn, diligent, ardent and resolute.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the Buddha replies, in that case, we could purify the very beginning of wholesome states.
[SPEAKER_00]: And what is the beginning of wholesome states?
[SPEAKER_00]: Here, Bhikkhu, you dwell restrained by the restraint of the patimokkha, accomplished in good conduct and proper resort, seeing danger in the slightest false, having undertaken the training rules, training them.
[SPEAKER_00]: When, Bhikkhu, you dwell restrained in such a way,
[SPEAKER_00]: Seeing the danger in the slightest fault, then, based upon that virtue, established upon virtue, you should develop the four establishments of mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_00]: The satipaṭṭhāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not before that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not before that, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you're doing your mindfulness before you even accomplish yourself in precepts.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just...
[SPEAKER_01]: Goes against...
[SPEAKER_01]: Putting the cart in front of a horse.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And expecting it to move.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's no way to have that type of a discernment.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, no.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, it's the same.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why it's mindfulness, samādhi.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the same development, same thing that comes on the basis of established, uncompromised, unbroken virtue.
[SPEAKER_00]: Uncompromised.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, how do you uncompromise?
[SPEAKER_01]: How do you not compromise your virtue?
[SPEAKER_01]: By overly defining your rules and sort of, you know, proliferating aspects or by simply not accepting any action that your mind offers you out of greed, aversion, delusion?
[SPEAKER_00]: And you know that.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you know that.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Am I acting out of hindrances?
[SPEAKER_01]: Am I acting out of doubt?
[SPEAKER_01]: Am I acting out of restlessness?
[SPEAKER_01]: Am I acting out of sensuality, anger, sloth and laziness?
[SPEAKER_01]: It's unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: If I don't do it, I am accomplishing virtue.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you will be abandoning hindrances as well, which is what samādhi is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not acting out of unwholesome states.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, we speak about it so, so, so often.
[SPEAKER_01]: And all of that is contained between you and your relationship with your own virtue or lack of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: When I say lack of virtue, it doesn't mean you don't keep the precepts.
[SPEAKER_01]: It means you keep them, but in that external, syllabar paramāsa sense, and you're not internally becoming accomplished in those rules.
[SPEAKER_01]: In other words, you're not internalizing criteria for unwholesome that you're avoiding.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're just adhering to the definition through your intellect, tradition, authority and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you're not... you don't have the clarity that comes from accomplishment in virtue,
[SPEAKER_00]: You cannot be mindful of the body.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, no.
[SPEAKER_01]: Your mindfulness will be external.
[SPEAKER_01]: In the same sense, your responsibility for your virtues is external.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, when you do mindfulness, you'll be doing it on the level of objects of your senses, which is not mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_01]: Duty.
[SPEAKER_01]: Will be like a duty.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's exactly what meditation technique is for people.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's often taken in a sense of another external duty that I must do.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it certainly
[SPEAKER_01]: It's always taken on the level of sense objects.
[SPEAKER_01]: Observations, nimittas and whatever else.
[SPEAKER_01]: Movements.
[SPEAKER_00]: Movements, motions.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's never taken as the internal... Recitations.
[SPEAKER_01]: Recitations, mantras.
[SPEAKER_00]: Visualizations.
[SPEAKER_01]: Visualizations, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's why it's taken there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because there is no basis for mindfulness, no sufficient basis for mindfulness to be taken on the right peripheral, sufficiently peripheral context.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what happens then, is just you take it where your mind is, and your mind is out there on the external things, because you want to avoid doubt and all these things, so you're just adhering to external things with a sense of duty.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sīlabhātaparamāsa.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then your meditation becomes on the level of that sīlabhātaparamāsa.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then your discernment is on that level.
[SPEAKER_01]: In other words, it's not a discernment.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're discerning things more on the level of sense objects without having the right context, the right basis for it.
[SPEAKER_01]: All because you haven't allowed yourself to become accomplished in that virtue correctly.
[SPEAKER_01]: You haven't taken it up.
[SPEAKER_01]: You haven't accepted the weight of responsibility for it and endured it.